<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>
        <string-array name="storyContents">
                <item>
Cyrus the Great, also called Cyrus II, (born 590–580 BCE, Media, or Persis [now in Iran]—died c. 529, Asia), conqueror who founded the Achaemenian empire, centred on Persia and comprising the Near East from the Aegean Sea eastward to the Indus River. He is also remembered in the Cyrus legend—first recorded by Xenophon, Greek soldier and author, in his Cyropaedia—as a tolerant and ideal monarch who was called the father of his people by the ancient Persians. In the Bible he is the liberator of the Jews who were captive in Babylonia.                </item>
            <item>Cyrus was born between 590 and 580 BCE, either in Media or, more probably, in Persis, the modern Fārs province of Iran. The meaning of his name is in dispute, for it is not known whether it was a personal name or a throne name given to him when he became a ruler. It is noteworthy that after the Achaemenian empire the name does not appear again in sources relating to Iran, which may indicate some special sense of the name.
            Most scholars agree, however, that Cyrus the Great was at least the second of the name to rule in Persia. One cuneiform text in Akkadian—the language of Mesopotamia (present-day Iraq) in the pre-Christian era—asserts he was the
            son of Cambyses, great king, king of Anshan, grandson of Cyrus, great king, king of Anshan, descendant of Teispes, great king, king of Anshan, of a family [which] always [exercised] kingship
            In any case, it is clear that Cyrus came from a long line of ruling chiefs.
            The most important source for his life is the Greek historian Herodotus. The idealized biography by Xenophon is a work for the edification of the Greeks concerning the ideal ruler, rather than a historical treatise. It does, however, indicate the high esteem in which Cyrus was held, not only by his own people, the Persians, but by the Greeks and others. Herodotus says that the Persians called Cyrus their father, while later Achaemenian rulers were not so well regarded. The story of the childhood of Cyrus, as told by Herodotus with echoes in Xenophon, may be called a Cyrus legend since it obviously follows a pattern of folk beliefs about the almost superhuman qualities of the founder of a dynasty. Similar beliefs also exist about the founders of later dynasties throughout the history of Iran. According to the legend, Astyages, the king of the Medes and overlord of the Persians, gave his daughter in marriage to his vassal in Persis, a prince called Cambyses. From this marriage Cyrus was born. Astyages, having had a dream that the baby would grow up to overthrow him, ordered Cyrus slain. His chief adviser, however, instead gave the baby to a shepherd to raise. When he was 10 years old, Cyrus, because of his outstanding qualities, was discovered by Astyages, who, in spite of the dream, was persuaded to allow the boy to live. Cyrus, when he reached manhood in Persis, revolted against his maternal grandfather and overlord. Astyages marched against the rebel, but his army deserted him and surrendered to Cyrus in 550 BCE.</item>
            <item>After inheriting the empire of the Medes, Cyrus first had to consolidate his power over Iranian tribes on the Iranian plateau before expanding to the west. Croesus, king of Lydia in Asia Minor (Anatolia), had enlarged his domains at the expense of the Medes when he heard of the fall of Astyages, and Cyrus, as successor of the Median king, marched against Lydia. Sardis, the Lydian capital, was captured in 547 or 546, and Croesus was either killed or burned himself to death, though according to other sources he was taken prisoner by Cyrus and well treated. The Ionian Greek cities on the Aegean Sea coast, as vassals of the Lydian king, now became subject to Cyrus, and most of them submitted after short sieges. Several revolts of the Greek cities were later suppressed with severity. Next Cyrus turned to Babylonia, where the dissatisfaction of the people with the ruler Nabonidus gave him a pretext for invading the lowlands. The conquest was quick, for even the priests of Marduk, the national deity of the great metropolis of Babylon, had become estranged from Nabonidus. In October 539 BCE, the greatest city of the ancient world fell to the Persians.

        In the Bible (e.g., Ezra 1:1–4), Cyrus is famous for freeing the Jewish captives in Babylonia and allowing them to return to their homeland. Cyrus was also tolerant toward the Babylonians and others. He conciliated local populations by supporting local customs and even sacrificing to local deities. The capture of Babylon delivered not only Mesopotamia into the hands of Cyrus but also Syria and Palestine, which had been conquered previously by the Babylonians. The ruler of Cilicia in Asia Minor had become an ally of Cyrus when the latter marched against Croesus, and Cilicia retained a special status in Cyrus’s empire. Thus it was by diplomacy as well as force of arms that he established the largest empire known until his time.

        Cyrus seems to have had several capitals. One was the city of Ecbatana, modern Hamadan, former capital of the Medes, and another was a new capital of the empire, Pasargadae, in Persis, said to be on the site where Cyrus had won the battle against Astyages. The ruins today, though few, arouse admiration in the visitor. Cyrus also kept Babylon as a winter capital.

        No Persian chauvinist, Cyrus was quick to learn from the conquered peoples. He not only conciliated the Medes but united them with the Persians in a kind of dual monarchy of the Medes and Persians. Cyrus had to borrow the traditions of kingship from the Medes, who had ruled an empire when the Persians were merely their vassals. A Mede was probably made an adviser to the Achaemenian king, as a sort of chief minister; on later reliefs at Persepolis, a capital of the Achaemenian kings from the time of Darius, a Mede is frequently depicted together with the great king. The Elamites, indigenous inhabitants of Persis, were also the teachers of the Persians in many ways, as can be seen, for example, in the Elamite dress worn by Persians and by Elamite objects carried by them on the stone reliefs at Persepolis. There also seems to have been little innovation in government and rule, but rather a willingness to borrow, combined with an ability to adapt what was borrowed to the new empire. Cyrus was undoubtedly the guiding genius in the creation not only of a great empire but in the formation of Achaemenian culture and civilization.

        Little is known of the family life of Cyrus. He had two sons, one of whom, Cambyses, succeeded him; the other, Bardiya (Smerdis of the Greeks), was probably secretly put to death by Cambyses after he became ruler. Cyrus had at least one daughter, Atossa (who married her brother Cambyses), and possibly two others, but they played no role in history.

        When Cyrus defeated Astyages he also inherited Median possessions in eastern Iran, but he had to engage in much warfare to consolidate his rule in this region. After his conquest of Babylonia, he again turned to the east, and Herodotus tells of his campaign against nomads living east of the Caspian Sea. According to the Greek historian, Cyrus was at first successful in defeating the ruler of the nomads—called the Massagetai—who was a woman, and captured her son. On the son’s committing suicide in captivity, his mother swore revenge and defeated and killed Cyrus. Herodotus’s story may be apocryphal, but Cyrus’s conquests in Central Asia were probably genuine, since a city in farthest Sogdiana was called Cyreschata, or Cyropolis, by the Greeks, which seems to prove the extent of his Eastern conquests.</item>                <item>Louisa was slow and still in her movements; it took her a long time to prepare her tea; but when ready it was set forth with as much grace as if she had been a veritable guest to her own self. The little square table stood exactly in the centre of the kitchen, and was covered with a starched linen cloth whose border pattern of flowers glistened. Louisa had a damask napkin on her tea-tray, where were arranged a cut-glass tumbler full of teaspoons, a silver cream-pitcher, a china sugar-bowl, and one pink china cup and saucer. Louisa used china every day — something which none of her neighbors did. They whispered about it among themselves. Their daily tables were laid with common crockery, their sets of best china stayed in the parlor closet, and Louisa Ellis was no richer nor better bred than they. Still she would use the china. She had for her supper a glass dish full of sugared currants, a plate of little cakes, and one of light white biscuits. Also a leaf or two of lettuce, which she cut up daintily. Louisa was very fond of lettuce, which she raised to perfection in her little garden. She ate quite heartily, though in a delicate, pecking way; it seemed almost surprising that any considerable bulk of the food should vanish.</item>

            It is a testimony to the capability of the founder of the Achaemenian empire that it continued to expand after his death and lasted for more than two centuries. But Cyrus was not only a great conqueror and administrator; he held a place in the minds of the Persian people similar to that of Romulus and Remus in Rome or Moses for the Israelites. His saga follows in many details the stories of hero and conquerors from elsewhere in the ancient world. The manner in which the baby Cyrus was given to a shepherd to raise is reminiscent of Moses in the bulrushes in Egypt, and the overthrow of his tyrannical grandfather has echoes in other myths and legends. There is no doubt that the Cyrus saga arose early among the Persians and was known to the Greeks. The sentiments of esteem or even awe in which Persians held him were transmitted to the Greeks, and it was no accident that Xenophon chose Cyrus to be the model of a ruler for the lessons he wished to impart to his fellow Greeks.

            In short, the figure of Cyrus has survived throughout history as more than a great man who founded an empire. He became the epitome of the great qualities expected of a ruler in antiquity, and he assumed heroic features as a conqueror who was tolerant and magnanimous as well as brave and daring. His personality as seen by the Greeks influenced them and Alexander the Great, and, as the tradition was transmitted by the Romans, may be considered to influence our thinking even now. In the year 1971, Iran celebrated the 2,500th anniversary of the founding of the monarchy by Cyrus.
            <item>Darius I, by name Darius the Great, (born 550 BC—died 486), king of Persia in 522–486 BC, one of the greatest rulers of the Achaemenid dynasty, who was noted for his administrative genius and for his great building projects. Darius attempted several times to conquer Greece; his fleet was destroyed by a storm in 492, and the Athenians defeated his army at Marathon in 490.</item>
            <item>Darius was the son of Hystaspes, the satrap (provincial governor) of Parthia. The principal contemporary sources for his history are his own inscriptions, especially the great trilingual inscription on the Bīsitūn (Behistun) rock at the village of the same name, in which he tells how he gained the throne. The accounts of his accession given by the Greek historians Herodotus and Ctesias are in many points obviously derived from this official version but are interwoven with legends.

        According to Herodotus, Darius, when a youth, was suspected by Cyrus II the Great (who ruled from 559 to 529 BC) of plotting against the throne. Later Darius was in Egypt with Cambyses II, the son of Cyrus and heir to his kingdom, as a member of the royal bodyguard. After the death of Cambyses in the summer of 522 BC, Darius hastened to Media, where, in September, with the help of six Persian nobles, he killed Bardiya (Smerdis), another son of Cyrus, who had usurped the throne the previous March. In the Bīsitūn inscription Darius defended this deed and his own assumption of kingship on the grounds that the usurper was actually Gaumata, a Magian, who had impersonated Bardiya after Bardiya had been murdered secretly by Cambyses. Darius therefore claimed that he was restoring the kingship to the rightful Achaemenid house. He himself, however, belonged to a collateral branch of the royal family, and, as his father and grandfather were alive at his accession, it is unlikely that he was next in line to the throne. Some modern scholars consider that he invented the story of Gaumata in order to justify his actions and that the murdered king was indeed the son of Cyrus.

        Darius did not at first gain general recognition but had to impose his rule by force. His assassination of Bardiya was followed, particularly in the eastern provinces, by widespread revolts, which threatened to disrupt the empire. In Susiana, Babylonia, Media, Sagartia, and Margiana, independent governments were set up, most of them by men who claimed to belong to the former ruling families. Babylonia rebelled twice and Susiana three times. In Persia itself a certain Vahyazdata, who pretended to be Bardiya, gained considerable support. These risings, however, were spontaneous and uncoordinated, and, notwithstanding the small size of his army, Darius and his generals were able to suppress them one by one. In the Bīsitūn inscription he records that in 19 battles he defeated nine rebel leaders, who appear as his captives on the accompanying relief. By 519 BC, when the third rising in Susiana was put down, he had established his authority in the east. In 518 Darius visited Egypt, which he lists as a rebel country, perhaps because of the insubordination of its satrap, Aryandes, whom he put to death.</item>
            <item>Having restored internal order in the empire, Darius undertook a number of campaigns for the purpose of strengthening his frontiers and checking the incursions of nomadic tribes. In 519 BC he attacked the Scythians east of the Caspian Sea and a few years later conquered the Indus Valley. In 513, after subduing eastern Thrace and the Getae, he crossed the Danube River into European Scythia, but the Scythian nomads devastated the country as they retreated from him, and he was forced, for lack of supplies, to abandon the campaign. The satraps of Asia Minor completed the subjugation of Thrace, secured the submission of Macedonia, and captured the Aegean islands of Lemnos and Imbros. Thus, the approaches to Greece were in Persian hands, as was control of the Black Sea grain trade through the straits, the latter being of major importance to the Greek economy. The conquest of Greece was a logical step to protect Persian rule over the Greeks of Asia Minor from interference by their European kinsmen. According to Herodotus, Darius, before the Scythian campaign, had sent ships to explore the Greek coasts, but he took no military action until 499 BC, when Athens and Eretria supported an Ionian revolt against Persian rule. After the suppression of this rebellion, Mardonius, Darius’ son-in-law, was given charge of an expedition against Athens and Eretria, but the loss of his fleet in a storm off Mount Athos (492 BC) forced him to abandon the operation. In 490 BC another force under Datis, a Mede, destroyed Eretria and enslaved its inhabitants but was defeated by the Athenians at Marathon. Preparations for a third expedition were delayed by an insurrection in Egypt, and Darius died in 486 BC before they were completed.</item>
            <item>Although Darius consolidated and added to the conquests of his predecessors, it was as an administrator that he made his greatest contribution to Persian history. He completed the organization of the empire into satrapies, initiated by Cyrus the Great, and fixed the annual tribute due from each province. During his reign, ambitious and far-sighted projects were undertaken to promote imperial trade and commerce. Coinage, weights, and measures were standardized and land and sea routes developed. An expedition led by Scylax of Caryanda sailed down the Indus River and explored the sea route from its mouth to Egypt, and a canal from the Nile River to the Red Sea, probably begun by the chief of the Egyptian delta lords, Necho I (7th century BC), was repaired and completed.

        While measures were thus taken to unite the diverse peoples of the empire by a uniform administration, Darius followed the example of Cyrus in respecting native religious institutions. In Egypt he assumed an Egyptian titulary and gave active support to the cult. He built a temple to the god Amon in the Kharga oasis, endowed the temple at Edfu, and carried out restoration work in other sanctuaries. He empowered the Egyptians to reestablish the medical school of the temple of Sais, and he ordered his satrap to codify the Egyptian laws in consultation with the native priests. In the Egyptian traditions he was considered as one of the great lawgivers and benefactors of the country. In 519 BC he authorized the Jews to rebuild the Temple at Jerusalem, in accordance with the earlier decree of Cyrus. In the opinion of some authorities, the religious beliefs of Darius himself, as reflected in his inscriptions, show the influence of the teachings of Zoroaster, and the introduction of Zoroastrianism as the state religion of Persia is probably to be attributed to him.

        Darius was the greatest royal architect of his dynasty, and during his reign Persian architecture assumed a style that remained unchanged until the end of the empire. In 521 BC he made Susa his administrative capital, where he restored the fortifications and built an audience hall (apadana) and a residential palace. The foundation inscriptions of his palace describe how he brought materials and craftsmen for the work from all quarters of the empire. At Persepolis, in his native country of Fars (Persis), he founded a new royal residence to replace the earlier capital at Pasargadae. The fortifications, apadana, council hall, treasury, and a residential palace are to be attributed to him, although not completed in his lifetime. He also built at Ecbana and Babylon.</item>
            <item>Cambyses II, (flourished 6th century BCE), Achaemenid king of Persia (reigned 529–522 BCE), who conquered Egypt in 525; he was the eldest son of King Cyrus II the Great by Cassandane, daughter of a fellow Achaemenid. During his father’s lifetime Cambyses was in charge of Babylonian affairs. In 538 he performed the ritual duties of a Babylonian king at the important New Year festival, and in 530, before Cyrus set out on his last campaign, he was appointed regent in Babylon.

        The conquest of Egypt, planned by Cyrus, was the major achievement of Cambyses’ reign. The invasion took place during the reign of Psamtik III. Cambyses received assistance from Polycrates of Samos; from Phanes, a Greek general in the Egyptian army who gave him valuable military information; and from the Arabs, who provided water for the crossing of the Sinai Desert. After Cambyses had won the Battle of Pelusium (525) in the Nile Delta and had captured Heliopolis and Memphis, Egyptian resistance collapsed.

        While in Egypt, Cambyses planned expeditions against Ethiopia, the Oasis of Amon (modern Wāḥat Sīwah), and Carthage. He himself set out against Ethiopia, but, after annexing the northern part of the country, he ran short of supplies and had to return. A detachment sent out from Thebes captured al-Kharijah (Kharga) Oasis but perished in a sandstorm before reaching the Oasis of Amon. The attack on Carthage was never attempted.

        The 5th-century-BCE Greek historian Herodotus accused Cambyses of many atrocities in Egypt, attributing them to madness, but contemporary Egyptian sources suggest that his accusations must largely be discounted. At least at the beginning of his rule, Cambyses pursued a conciliatory policy.

        According to a later Achaemenid king, Darius I the Great, Cambyses, before going to Egypt, had secretly killed his brother, Bardiya, whom Herodotus called Smerdis. The murdered prince was, however, impersonated by Gaumata the Magian, who in March 522 seized the Achaemenid throne. Cambyses was traveling through Syria on his way back to Persia when he first heard reports of the revolt there; he died mysteriously in Syria in the summer of 522, either by his own hand or as the result of an accident.</item>
            <item>Bardiya, also called Smerdis, (died 522 BCE), a son of Cyrus the Great of Persia and possible king of Persia in 522 BCE, although some accounts claim the king known as Bardiya was an impersonator of that son.

        The Greek historian Herodotus and the Persian king Darius, in his inscription at Bīsitūn, state that Bardiya was murdered by his brother, Cambyses II, but was later successfully impersonated by Gaumata, a Magian, who was able to seize the throne when Cambyses died in 522 BCE. The usurper reigned for only eight months, however, before he was slain by Darius and other Persian nobles suspicious of his origin. Certain modern historians consider that Darius, who succeeded to the throne, invented the story of Gaumata to justify his actions and that the murdered king had indeed been a son of Cyrus.</item>
            <item>Xerxes I, Old Persian Khshayarsha, byname Xerxes the Great, (born c. 519 BCE—died 465, Persepolis, Iran), Persian king (486–465 BCE), the son and successor of Darius I. He is best known for his massive invasion of Greece from across the Hellespont (480 BCE), a campaign marked by the battles of Thermopylae, Salamis, and Plataea. His ultimate defeat spelled the beginning of the decline of the Achaemenian Empire.</item>
            <item>Xerxes was the son of Darius I and Atossa, daughter of Cyrus; he was the first son born to Darius after his accession to the throne. Xerxes was designated heir apparent by his father in preference to his elder brother Artabazanes. A bas-relief on the southern portico of a courtyard in the treasury of Persepolis, as well as the bas-reliefs on the east door of the tripylon (an ornamental stairway) depict him as the heir apparent, standing behind his father, who is seated on the throne. When his father died, in 486 BCE, Xerxes was about 35 years old and had already governed Babylonia for a dozen years.

        One of his first concerns upon his accession was to pacify Egypt, where a usurper had been governing for two years. But he was forced to use much stronger methods than had Darius: in 484 BCE he ravaged the Delta and chastised the Egyptians. Xerxes then learned of the revolt of Babylon, where two nationalist pretenders had appeared in swift succession. The second, Shamash-eriba, was conquered by Xerxes’ son-in-law, and violent repression ensued: Babylon’s fortresses were torn down, its temples pillaged, and the statue of Marduk destroyed. This latter act had great political significance: Xerxes was no longer able to “take the hand of” (receive the patronage of) the Babylonian god. Whereas Darius had treated Egypt and Babylonia as kingdoms personally united to the Achaemenian Empire (though administered as satrapies), Xerxes acted with a new intransigence. Having rejected the fiction of personal union, he then abandoned the titles of king of Babylonia and king of Egypt, making himself simply “king of the Persians and the Medes.”

        It was probably the revolt of Babylon, although some authors say it was troubles in Bactria, to which Xerxes alluded in an inscription that proclaimed:

        And among these countries (in rebellion) there was one where, previously, daevas had been worshipped. Afterward, through Ahura Mazdā’s favour, I destroyed this sanctuary of daevas and proclaimed, “Let daevas not be worshipped!” There, where daevas had been worshipped before, I worshipped Ahura Mazdā.

        Xerxes thus declared himself the adversary of the daevas, the ancient pre-Zoroastrian gods, and doubtlessly identified the Babylonian gods with these fallen gods of the Aryan religion. The questions arise of whether the destruction of Marduk’s statue should be linked with this text proclaiming the destruction of the daeva sanctuaries, of whether Xerxes was a more zealous supporter of Zoroastrianism than was his father, and, indeed, of whether he himself was a Zoroastrian. The problem of the relationship between the Achaemenian religion and Zoroastrianism is a difficult one, and some scholars, such as M. Molé, have even thought that this is an improper posing of the question—that there were, rather, three different states of religion: a religion of strict observance, a royal religion as attested by the Achaemenian inscriptions, and the popular religion as described by the Greek historian Herodotus.</item>

            <item>With the tranquillity of the empire reestablished, Xerxes would willingly have devoted himself to peaceful activities. But many of those around him were pressing for the renewal of hostilities. His cousin and brother-in-law Mardonius, supported by a strong party of exiled Greeks, incited him to take revenge for the affront that Darius had suffered at the hands of the Greeks at Marathon (490 BCE). The impressionable Xerxes gave way to pressure from his entourage and threw himself into patient diplomatic and military preparations for war, which required three years to complete (484–481 BCE). Herodotus notes that never before had such an effort been undertaken. Troops were levied in all the satrapies, and a navy, intended to be the army’s supply line, was gathered. The care lavished on this enterprise shows that the king did not regard it as a minor operation.

        There has been much later speculation on the real causes for the expedition. They could not have been economic, because Greece was not important then. Perhaps it was only the manifestation of a royal absolutism: Xerxes, whose character was later distorted in Greek legend, was neither foolish nor overly optimistic; although sensible and intelligent, he was nevertheless, according to G. Glotz,
        a sovereign by divine right, to whom opposition was as annoying as sacrilege…nervous in temperament, fallen from youthful fire into indolence, incited to make a war he didn’t like.

        At the head of his armies, he left Sardis for the Hellespont and had two boat bridges placed across the strait. A storm destroyed them, and Xerxes had the sea whipped as punishment. With the bridges remade, for seven days he oversaw the crossing of the army—5,000,000 men according to Herodotus and 360,000 by modern estimate, supported by 700 to 800 ships. Their passage was facilitated by a massive engineering works: a channel was dug across the Isthmus of Actium so that the peaks of Mount Athos might be avoided. Nevertheless, the army’s size was of no help, partly because of misinformation about the enemy terrain and partly because of the appearance of a national feeling in Greece. After a few successes (e.g., Thermopylae, mid-August 480 BCE), Xerxes occupied Attica and pillaged Athens on September 21, but on September 29, at Salamis, a naval battle that he had initiated turned into a defeat. Without a fleet to take supplies to the army, he had to retreat; he crossed over into Asia, leaving Mardonius in Thessaly. During an indecisive battle near Plataea on August 27, 479 BCE, Mardonius was killed, and his death obliged the army of occupation to withdraw. Hostilities continued for 13 years, but thenceforth Xerxes involved himself only slightly.</item>

            <item>Soured by this failure, which modern historians consider the beginning of Achaemenian decline, Xerxes retired to Susa and Persepolis. He then furthered the depletion of the once-enormous resources he had gathered, through multiple taxation, by launching a vast construction program. At the capital city of Persepolis, Darius’ architects, working from a unified plan of great scope, had already begun construction on a gigantic terrace of the Apadana (an audience hall), the Tripylon, a palace, and a treasury. When Xerxes became king, he had laid the enameled-brick facing on the exterior of the Apadana and finished his father’s palace. Then he erected other monuments: his own palace, southeast of Darius’ and similar to it in plan, and a mysterious building called the Harem by archaeologists—a line of small, identical rooms that may have been Xerxes’ treasury. He also undertook construction of the Hall of a Hundred Columns, or Throne Room, but he was able to finish only the paving and the base of the walls (the walls themselves and the decoration of this gigantic hypostyle hall were the work of Artaxerxes I). These buildings marked an evolution toward the colossal and toward a style that was perhaps more pretentious than that typical of Darius’ reign.

        Little is known about the last years of Xerxes’ life. After his reversal in Greece, he withdrew into himself and allowed himself to be drawn into harem intrigues in which he was, in fact, only a pawn; thus, he disposed of his brother’s entire family at the demand of the queen. But in 465 BCE he himself fell, together with his eldest son, under the blows of murderous members of his court, among them his minister Artabanus. Another son, Artaxerxes I, succeeded in retaining power.</item>

            <item>Artaxerxes I, (died 425 BC, Susa, Elam [now in Iran]), Achaemenid king of Persia (reigned 465–425 BC).

        He was surnamed in Greek Macrocheir (“Longhand”) and in Latin Longimanus. A younger son of Xerxes I and Amestris, he was raised to the throne by the commander of the guard, Artabanus, who had murdered Xerxes. A few months later, Artaxerxes slew Artabanus in a hand-to-hand fight. His reign, though generally peaceful, was disturbed by several insurrections, the first of which was the revolt of his brother the satrap of Bactria. More dangerous was the rebellion of Egypt under Inaros, who received assistance from the Athenians. Achaemenid rule in Egypt was restored by Megabyzus, satrap of Syria, after a prolonged struggle (460–454). In 448 fighting between the Achaemenids and the Athenians ended, and in the Samian and Peloponnesian wars Artaxerxes remained neutral; toward the Jews he pursued a tolerant policy. His building inscriptions at Persepolis record the completion of the throne hall of his father. The tomb of Artaxerxes is at Naqsh-e Rustam.</item>

            <item>Xerxes II (r.425-424 BC) was a very short lived ruler of the Persian Empire, who was killed by the son of one of his father\'s concubines after a reign of only 45 days. His father, Artaxerxes I (r.464-425 BC) had been a moderately successful ruler who had achieved some successes against the Greeks before his death in 425 BC. His only legitimate son came to the throne as Xerxes II, but only forty-five days later, while in a drunker stupor, he was killed on the orders of his half brother, the son of one of his father\'s concubines (named Sogdianus or Secundianus). The murderer was killed himself a few months later, and his killer took the throne as Darius II (r.423-404 BC), another fairly weak ruler who allowed control of relations with the Greeks to fall into the hands of the governors of Asia Minor. It is likely that Sogdianus and Darius claimed the throne at about the same time, as the gap between the last known tablet from the reign of Artaxerxes and the first of Darius is only seventeen days (although this could reflect a later desire to wipe the two short-lived reigns from the record).</item>

            <item>Darius II Ochus, (died 404 BCE, Babylon [now in Iraq]), Achaemenid king (reigned 423–404 BCE) of Persia.

        The son of Artaxerxes I by a Babylonian concubine, he seized the throne from his half brother Secydianus (or Sogdianus), whom he then executed. Ochus, who had previously been satrap of Hyrcania, adopted the name of Darius on his accession; he was also known as Nothus (from the Greek nothos, meaning “bastard”). Darius was dominated by eunuchs and by his half sister and wife, the cruel and ambitious Parysatis. Intrigue and corruption were rife at the Achaemenid court, and revolts in Hyrcania and Media, although quickly suppressed, were symptomatic of the discontent caused by his rule.

        After the Athenian defeat at Syracuse in 413 BCE, Darius decided to recover the Greek coastal cities of Asia Minor, which had been under Athenian control since 448. The satraps of Asia Minor, Tissaphernes and Pharnabazus, were ordered to collect overdue tribute, and an alliance against Athens was formed with Sparta. In the ensuing war the greater part of Ionia was recovered, but elsewhere the allies had less success, partly because of the policy of Tissaphernes, who gave Spartan forces only limited support. In 407, however, Darius decided to put all his resources behind Sparta. He appointed his son Cyrus the Younger in place of Tissaphernes as commander in chief of Asia Minor and gave him funds to re-create the Spartan fleet. As a result Athenian power was broken in 405 at Aegospotami. Not long after, Darius died of an illness.</item>

            <item>Artaxerxes II, (flourished late 5th and early 4th centuries BC), Achaemenid king of Persia (reigned 404–359/358).

        He was the son and successor of Darius II and was surnamed (in Greek) Mnemon, meaning “the mindful.” When Artaxerxes took the Persian throne, the power of Athens had been broken in the Peloponnesian War (431–404), and the Greek towns across the Aegean Sea in Ionia were again subjects of the Achaemenid Empire. In 404, however, Artaxerxes lost Egypt, and in the following year his brother Cyrus the Younger began preparations for his rebellion. Although Cyrus was defeated and killed at Cunaxa (401), the rebellion had dangerous repercussions, for it not only demonstrated the superiority of the Greek hoplites used by Cyrus but also led the Greeks to believe that Persia was vulnerable.

        In 400 Sparta broke openly with the Achaemenids, and during the next five years its armies achieved considerable military success in Anatolia. The Spartan navy, however, was destroyed at Cnidus (394), thereby giving the Achaemenids mastery of the Aegean. The Greek allies of Persia (Thebes, Athens, Argos, and Corinth) continued the war against Sparta, but, when it became evident that the only ones to gain from the war were the Athenians, Artaxerxes decided to conclude peace with Sparta. In 386 Athens was compelled to accept the settlement known as the King’s Peace, or the Peace of Antalcidas, by which Artaxerxes decreed that all the Asiatic mainland and Cyprus were his, that Lemnos, Imbros, and Scyros were to remain Athenian dependencies, and that all the other Greek states were to receive autonomy.

        Elsewhere Artaxerxes met with less success. Two expeditions against Egypt (385–383 and 374) ended in complete failure, and during the same period there were continuous rebellions in Anatolia. There were also wars against the mountain tribes of Armenia and Iran.

        By the King’s Peace the Achaemenids had become the arbiters of Greece, and in the following wars all parties applied to them for a decision in their favour. After the Theban victory of Leuctra (371), an old alliance between the Achaemenids and the Thebans was restored. Achaemenid supremacy, however, was based on Greek internal discord rather than Achaemenid strength, and, when this weakness became apparent, all the satraps (governors) of Anatolia rose in revolt (c. 366), in alliance with Athens, Sparta, and Egypt, and Artaxerxes could do little against them. The satraps, however, were divided by mutual distrust, and the rebellion was finally put down by Persia through a series of treacheries. When the reign of Artaxerxes ended, Achaemenid authority had been restored over most of the empire—more from internal rivalries and discord than from his efforts.

        Under Artaxerxes an important change occurred in the Persian religion. The Persians apparently did not worship images of the gods until Artaxerxes set up statues of the goddess Anāhitā in various large cities. Inscriptions by all former kings named only Ahura Mazdā, but those of Artaxerxes also invoked Anāhitā and Mithra, two deities of the old popular Iranian religion that had been neglected.</item>

            <item>Artaxerxes III, (died 338 BC), Achaemenid king of Persia (reigned 359/358–338 BC).
        He was the son and successor of Artaxerxes II and was called Ochus before he took the throne. Artaxerxes III was a cruel but energetic ruler. To secure his throne he put to death most of his relatives. In 356 he ordered all the satraps (governors) of the Achaemenid empire to dismiss their mercenaries. He also forced Athens to conclude peace and to acknowledge the independence of its rebellious allies (355).

        Artaxerxes then attempted to subjugate Egypt, which had been independent since 404. Failure of the first attempt (351) encouraged the Phoenician towns and the princes of Cyprus to revolt. Early in 345, Artaxerxes collected a great army and marched against the Phoenician city of Sidon. Mentor of Rhodes, who had helped betray Sidon, rose high in the king’s favour and entered into a close understanding with the eunuch Bagoas, the king’s favourite. Artaxerxes then advanced on Egypt with a great land and naval force and, at Pelusium in the Nile River delta, defeated the pharaoh Nectanebo II (343). A Persian satrap was placed over Egypt, the walls of its cities were destroyed, its temples were plundered, and Artaxerxes was said to have killed the Apis bull with his own hand.

        After the king’s return to Susa, Bagoas ruled the court and the upper satrapies, while Mentor restored the authority of the empire throughout the west. When Philip of Macedon attacked Perinthus and Byzantium (340), Artaxerxes sent support to those cities. In 338 Artaxerxes and his elder sons were killed by Bagoas, who then raised the king’s youngest son, Arses, to the throne.</item>

            <item>Arses was a son of the Persian king Artaxerxes III Ochus (358-338), and succeeded his
        father. According to a Greek source, Diodorus of Sicily, the powerful eunuch Bagoas poisoned
        many members of the royal family, but a cuneiform tablet in the British Museum (BM 71537)
        suggests that the king died from natural causes. However this may be, it happened in
        September 338, and it is probable that Bagoas killed everyone to make sure that Arses, who
        is presented by Diodorus as some sort of a puppet king, became the new ruler of the
        Achaemenid empire. Alternatively, Arses ordered the executions himself. This is not
        uncommon.

        From an inscription from Xanthus, we know that Arses accepted the same throne name as his
        father and grandfather, Artaxerxes.

        The death of Artaxerxes III caused great upheavals in the Achaemenid empire and it is
        certain that Bagoas and Artaxerxes IV were unable to get a firm grasp on the situation. At
        least two satrapies revolted: Egypt, which had recently been conquered by Artaxerxes III,
        and Babylonia (although the evidence for the insurrection of Nidin-Bêl is meager). To add to
        these troubles, the king of Macedonia, Philip II, prepared an attack on Persia\'s possessions
        in what is now Turkey. His trusted general Parmenion crossed the Hellespont in the spring of
        336, and several Greek cities sided with the invader.

        Under these circumstances, it comes as no surprise that the Persian nobility was divided.
        Prince Artašata, a distant relative of Artaxerxes and satrap of Armenia, seems to exercised
        pressure. He was a powerful man and a formidable warrior, and he received support from
        several noblemen (e.g., Pharnabazus). Diodorus says that Artaxerxes wanted to remove Bagoas
        (text) and that this forced Bagoas to kill this king as well (summer of 336). The cuneiform
        text known as the Dynastic prophecy suggests that Artašata marched on Persepolis and seized
        the throne. Whatever may have happened, Artašata now became king under the name of Darius
        III Codomannus.

        One of his first acts was the execution of Bagoas. For a few months there was a respite:
        there was a strong king who was able to reunite the kingdom, and Philip was murdered
        (October 336). Moreover, a Greek mercenary general in Persian service, Memnon of Rhodes, was
        able to push back Parmenion. However, Philip was succeeded by his young son Alexander the
        Great, who joined Parmenion (May 334), and launched the campaign that ended with the fall of
        the Achaemenid empire and the death of Darius III (330).

        There is one badly damaged source, quoted here, that suggests that Artaxerxes decided to
        restore the Babylonian temples Esagila and Etemenanki. The project was executed by
        Alexander.

        The reign of Artaxerxes IV Arses was short but important, because the seeds were sown for
        the ultimate downfall of Persia.</item>

            <item>Darius III, also called Codommanus, (died 330 BC, Bactria), the last king (reigned 336–330 BC) of the Achaemenid dynasty.

        Darius belonged to a collateral branch of the royal family and was placed on the throne by the eunuch Bagoas, who had poisoned the two previous kings, Artaxerxes III and Arses. When Darius asserted his independence, Bagoas also attempted his murder but was forced by the king to drink the poison himself.

        In 337 Philip II of Macedon had formed the League of Corinth for the purpose of liberating the Greek cities under Achaemenid rule and, early in 336, had sent an advance force into Asia Minor. In July, however, he was assassinated, perhaps at the instigation of Darius. In the spring of 334 Philip’s son Alexander the Great crossed the Hellespont. Because Darius had made no serious preparations to resist the invasion, Alexander defeated an Achaemenid army at the Granicus and, by the following year, had won most of Asia Minor and reached Cilicia. Darius finally advanced against him but was defeated at Issus in the autumn of 333. Darius fled from the field, abandoning his mother, wife, and children.

        Darius twice sent Alexander a letter of friendship, the second time offering a large ransom for his family, cession of all the Achaemenid Empire west of the Euphrates River, and the hand of his daughter in return for an alliance. Alexander rejected both letters and marched into Mesopotamia. Darius made no attempt to resist his crossing of the Euphrates and Tigris but offered battle at Gaugamela, east of modern Mosul. On Oct. 1, 331, he was decisively defeated, and, as at Issus, he turned his chariot and fled, although his subordinates fought on. He escaped to Ecbatana, and then, on the approach of Alexander, he retired toward Bactria but was deposed and killed by the Bactrian satrap Bessus.</item>

        </string-array>
</resources>